<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Provision Software LLC</title>
    <link>https://www.provision-software.com/tags/web/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Provision Software LLC</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright (c) 2016 - 2020 Provision Software LLC; all rights reserved.</copyright>
    <atom:link href="https://www.provision-software.com/tags/web/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>RMH Trucking Sample Site</title>
      <link>https://www.provision-software.com/blog/2018/06/05/rmh-trucking/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jun 2018 13:47:08 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.provision-software.com/blog/2018/06/05/rmh-trucking/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;rmh-trucking-small-sample-site&#34;&gt;RMH Trucking Small Sample Site&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently decided to change up my focus a little bit from &amp;ldquo;Android Development&amp;rdquo; or even more general with &amp;ldquo;Mobile Development&amp;rdquo;
and focus on web development. I decided that I was going to try solve a problem I am very familiar with, terrible or non-existing
websites for trucking companies. Even more specifically than that, websites that are outdated and not mobile friendly for
trucking companies that specialize in liquid bulk transportation. I got the idea from
&lt;a href=&#34;https://entrepreneurs.maqtoob.com/how-to-get-jobs-on-freelance-sites-even-if-you-have-zero-experience-6df6a660ff1b&#34;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt;
that you can check out, but it basically says to be highly specialized instead of highly generalized in order to better compete
as a freelancer. That is when I realized that I am intimately familiar with trucking companies and many have terrible or no websites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I created RMH Trucking as a sample of what I can do. It is called RMH Trucking Small because it is the &amp;ldquo;small&amp;rdquo; offering I have.
I will also be creating a RMH Trucking Medium and RMH Trucking Large for those companies looking for more comprehensive sites.
For now you can check out &lt;a href=&#34;https://ryanmhoffman.github.io/RMHTruckingSmall&#34;&gt;RMH Trucking Small here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-importance&#34;&gt;The Importance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This site and the others once created will offer a look and design like they are modern, but they will more importantly scale
well for mobile devices. The most common thing I see is a slightly outdated desktop site that isn&amp;rsquo;t terrible, but on mobile
it becomes completely unusable. My sites will be completely mobile friendly, look great, and will be customizable to match
the brand of any company. Also, they will be optomized to rank highly in search engines so potential new customers and
drivers can find the company and easily get in contact with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will come back and update this with the other sample sites once they are created, so stay tuned for those updates. If you
are looking to have a site built or redesigned for your trucking company (or any other company), feel free to
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.provision-software.com/contact/&#34;&gt;contact&lt;/a&gt; me for more details!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>