<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Provision Software LLC</title>
    <link>https://www.provision-software.com/tags/text-editor/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Provision Software LLC</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright (c) 2016 - 2020 Provision Software LLC; all rights reserved.</copyright>
    <atom:link href="https://www.provision-software.com/tags/text-editor/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Nearly 8 Months with Vim</title>
      <link>https://www.provision-software.com/blog/2017/12/27/update-on-vim/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Dec 2017 13:47:08 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.provision-software.com/blog/2017/12/27/update-on-vim/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;how-i-feel-about-vim-now&#34;&gt;How I Feel About Vim Now&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is a follow up on a post I wrote several months ago about my starting point with Vim. If you missed that post, you can
read it &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.provision-software.com/blog/2017/04/28/getting-started-with-vim/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. That details how and when I started with Vim nearly 8 months ago.
Now it is an integral part of my workflow. It is my only text editor, and I don&amp;rsquo;t know how I lived without it before. The intention
isn&amp;rsquo;t to preach Vim here and force it on anyone; I am merely chronicling my adventures in learning this editor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-i-use-vim&#34;&gt;How I use Vim&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vim is my general text editor now, used for pretty much everything but Java and Kotlin (Android development). I use it for
Python, editing my configs, even writing this post in Markdown. I have personalized my vimrc a little bit, but it is actually
still very small. I use a few plugins too, but again they are very few. I have found that Vim does a lot of things that many
people might not know about and try to use plugins for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond jusing actual Vim in the terminal, I also have begun using plugins wherever possible to add Vim bindings to different
applications. I have added IdeaVim to Intellij Idea and Android Studio to configure as many keys as possible to behave like
Vim. It is very good, but not perfect. It definitely is good enough to recommend to about any Vim user out there. I also use
Vimium extension in Vivaldi, my browser. It is an extension for Chrome technically, but since Vivaldi is based on the
chromium open source project same as Chrome, the extensions mostly work on it. Vimium uses many of the navigation key bindings
from Vim and adds some to help with link navigation etc. It makes it possible to use the broswer mostly without a mouse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-vim-configuration&#34;&gt;My Vim Configuration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My Vim config is pretty small, but it does have some changes, almost none are unique to me. I find things from other people&amp;rsquo;s
configs and use them, just like everyone else does. Some big changes I have made are remapping the escape key to jj. Other
than typing it right there, I have never had to type two j&amp;rsquo;s together before, so it is a safe string to use. It is on the
home row so I don&amp;rsquo;t have to stretch for escape every time I want to exit insert mode. For plugins, I have added Nerdtree
for easy file navigation, I added YouCompleteMe code completion engine, and I have added powerline. I use relative line
numbers for easy jumping from line to line. The last customizations I made are just visual, I use syntax highlighting and
the color scheme I have set is darcula, which looks like the theme of the same name in Jetbrains IDEs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;where-i-m-going-from-here&#34;&gt;Where I&amp;rsquo;m Going From Here&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vim is my main editor now, and I can&amp;rsquo;t see myself switching any time soon. That doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean I will never try something else,
but I have become so much more productive with Vim that it feels like a waste to use anything else now. I don&amp;rsquo;t want to be
a vim evangelist, preaching it to all. It simply is the best editor for me and my workflow. That does not mean it is for
everyone, nor should it be. I might make tutorials some day about Vim, but for now, I am just a happy user.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting Started with Vim</title>
      <link>https://www.provision-software.com/blog/2017/04/28/getting-started-with-vim/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Apr 2017 13:47:08 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.provision-software.com/blog/2017/04/28/getting-started-with-vim/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;getting-started-with-vim&#34;&gt;Getting Started with Vim&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The title of this article might be misleading a little bit, but this is not a tutorial about how to get started with Vim.
It is in fact a small post about my decision to get started with Vim. I recently made the decision to start using Vim as
my main (read only) editor. I decided that I&amp;rsquo;m going to give it a try for 37 days, and after that I will see if I like it
and if it makes me any more productive than with my current editor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;starting-point&#34;&gt;Starting Point&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other than a minimal knowledge of what Vim was, I knew nothing about using it or how to get started. I installed it on all
my machines about 3 days ago, and now I&amp;rsquo;m already using it full time. I&amp;rsquo;m still very slow, I have to look up commands about
every other minute, and I constantly stop to tweak my .vimrc but I&amp;rsquo;m learning quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to start with a blank slate. I used a pure vanilla install of Vim, and I created a blank .vimrc as a starting point.
I wanted to follow the advice that said you shouldn&amp;rsquo;t start with someone else&amp;rsquo;s configuration, and don&amp;rsquo;t put anything in your
.vimrc that you don&amp;rsquo;t understand. It&amp;rsquo;s working for me so far, but as I mentioned I&amp;rsquo;ve only been using it for a few days now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;basic-commands&#34;&gt;Basic Commands&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got the basics down for navigation through the file, and basic editing with delete, copy/paste and insert. I&amp;rsquo;m trying my
best stay in normal mode as much as possible and only switch to insert mode when necessary. It&amp;rsquo;s slower for me right now, but
I can already see how it will get faster once I get the commands into my fingers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;where-i-m-going-from-here&#34;&gt;Where I&amp;rsquo;m Going From Here&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m going to continue to only use Vim for the next 30 days. At the end of May, I&amp;rsquo;m going to post an update on whether I plan
to stick with Vim, and either way I&amp;rsquo;m going to give my complete and honest thoughts on using it. I will explain how it made me
more or less productive and if it was worth learning all the commands and keyboard shortcuts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I should also mention that I have installed IdeaVim plugin for Intellij IDEA and Android Studio. I do the majority of my
development in Android Studio since I&amp;rsquo;m an Android developer, so I figured to really double down and get the full experience
I need Vim everywhere. Stay tuned for the update next month and happy Vimming!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>