<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ryan M. Hoffman</title>
    <link>https://ryanmhoffman.github.io/tags/development/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Ryan M. Hoffman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright (c) 2016 - 2017 RMH Companies; all rights reserved.</copyright>
    <atom:link href="https://ryanmhoffman.github.io/tags/development/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting Started with Vim</title>
      <link>https://ryanmhoffman.github.io/blog/2017/04/28/getting-started-with-vim/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Apr 2017 13:47:08 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ryanmhoffman.github.io/blog/2017/04/28/getting-started-with-vim/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;getting-started-with-vim&#34;&gt;Getting Started with Vim&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The title of this article might be misleading a litle bit, but this is not a tutorial about how to get started with Vim. It is in fact a small post about my decision to get started with Vim. I recently made the decision to start using Vim as my main (read only) editor. I decided that I&amp;rsquo;m going to give it a try for 30 days, and after that I will see if I like it and if it makes me any more productive than with my current editor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;starting-point&#34;&gt;Starting Point&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other than a minimal knowledge of what Vim was, I knew nothing about using it or how to get started. I installed it on all my machines about 3 days ago, and now I&amp;rsquo;m already using it full time. I&amp;rsquo;m still very slow, I have to look up commands about every other minute, and I constantly stop to tweak my .vimrc but I&amp;rsquo;m learning quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to start with a blank slate. I used a pure vanilla install of Vim, and I created a blank .vimrc as a starting point. I wanted to follow the advice that said you shouldn&amp;rsquo;t start with someone else&amp;rsquo;s configuration, and don&amp;rsquo;t put anything in your .vimrc that you don&amp;rsquo;t understand. It&amp;rsquo;s working for me so far, but as I mentioned I&amp;rsquo;ve only been using it for a few days now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;basic-commands&#34;&gt;Basic Commands&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got the basics down for navigation through the file, and basic editing with delete, copy/paste and insert. I&amp;rsquo;m trying my best stay in normal mode as much as possible and only switch to insert mode when necessary. It&amp;rsquo;s slower for me right now, but I can already see how it will get faster once I get the commands into my fingers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;where-i-m-going-from-here&#34;&gt;Where I&amp;rsquo;m Going From Here&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m going to continue to only use Vim for the next 30 days. At the end of May, I&amp;rsquo;m going to post an update on whether I plan to stick with Vim, and either way I&amp;rsquo;m going to give my complete and honest thoughts on using it. I will explain how it made me more or less productive and if it was worth learning all the commands and keyboard shortcuts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I should also mention that I have installed IdeaVim plugin for Intellij IDEA and Android Studio. I do the majority of my development in Android Studio since I&amp;rsquo;m an Android developer, so I figured to really double down and get the full experience I need Vim everywhere. Stay tuned for the update next month and happy Vimming!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Android Terminology Overview</title>
      <link>https://ryanmhoffman.github.io/blog/2017/03/01/android-terminology/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2017 13:47:08 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ryanmhoffman.github.io/blog/2017/03/01/android-terminology/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;android-unit-of-measure-terminology&#34;&gt;Android Unit of Measure Terminology&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have you ever wondered why there are so many different units of measurement in the Android architecture? There is dp, dip, sp, px, pt, in and mm. Below I will run through what each one is and what their purpose is within the Android framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;px&#34;&gt;PX&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;View
  android:layout_width:&amp;quot;50px&amp;quot;
  android:layout_height:&amp;quot;wrap_content&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Android, px is short for pixels. It corresponds to actual pixels on the screen. In this example the view would be exactly 50 pixels wide. This is useful for getting your layout pixel perfect, but there is a catch when using px. The pixel density on the screen will vary across devices. The higher the pixel density is, the smaller the view will appear, even though it will still be 50px.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;dp-dip&#34;&gt;DP/DIP&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;View
  android:layout_width:&amp;quot;50dp&amp;quot;
  android:layout_height:&amp;quot;50dip&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DP and DIP are actually the same thing and can be used interchangeably. They stand for Density Independent Pixels. This is one of the most useful measurements for designing across multiple screen densities and having everything lay out properly. Density independent pixels scale views so they lay out proportionally across various pixel densities. On a screen with a pixel density of 160dpi, 1dp is the same as 1px. As the pixel density increases for  higher resolution display, the ratio of dp to px will change. If you use dp/dip as the unit of measure, Android will decide the correct ratio for you so the views stay proportional across screens with various pixel densities. This is probably the most common unit used due to how easy it is to design across devices with minimal issues. It is worth noting that while dp and dip can be used interchangeably, dp is more commonly used because not only is it one less character to type, but it also corresponds with sp as you will see next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;sp&#34;&gt;SP&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;TextView
  android:textSize=&amp;quot;18sp&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SP stands for Scale Independent Pixels. SP is very similar to DP/DIP, with one main difference. Scale independent pixels adjust based on pixel density and user preference. This means if the user is visually impaired and specifies Large Text in their settings, sp will scale appropriately on their device. It is mainly used on text, but it can also be used on views containing text to ensure they expand to fit the text properly. If there are no custom settings specified on the user&amp;rsquo;s device, sp will behave exactly the same as dp/dip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;pt&#34;&gt;PT&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;View
  android:layout_width:&amp;quot;25pt&amp;quot;
  android:layout_height:&amp;quot;35pt&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PT is short for Point, and it is simply &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;72&lt;/sub&gt; of an inch. This assumes a screen with 72dpi (dots per inch.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;mm-and-in&#34;&gt;MM and IN&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;View
  android:layout_width:&amp;quot;1in&amp;quot;
  android:layout_height:&amp;quot;15mm&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MM is the abbreviation for millimeters, and IN is the abbreviation for inches. These units refer to actual sizes and ignore factors like pixel density and screen size. Using a value like &amp;ldquo;1in&amp;rdquo; means the view will take up exactly 1 inch of screen real estate, and the same is true for millimeters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When designing layouts on Android, dp and sp are definitely the most commonly used units due to how easily they scale across different screens. It is always recommended that you test your layouts on as many different screen sizes as possible to ensure that everything is laid out as expected. Even with the units that scale across pixel densities there can still be inconsistencies, so never trust that your layout will look exactly like it does in the preview in Android Studio.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Friends Android App</title>
      <link>https://ryanmhoffman.github.io/blog/2016/12/20/friends-android-app/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Dec 2016 13:47:08 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ryanmhoffman.github.io/blog/2016/12/20/friends-android-app/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;friends-android-app&#34;&gt;Friends Android App&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Friends is an Android app I am currently developing with a planned release in early January 2017. The app
is a short-list version of the stock contacts app. Friends pulls in only your starred contacts and gives
you easy access to call or text them. It is supposed to be sort of like a speed dial, but for all your
favorites instead of just one, and all in one place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-idea&#34;&gt;The Idea&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I originally began building this app as a generic replacement to the stock contacts app on Android. As I
was building it I began wondering what feature I would have that would set it apart. I thought about the
idea of somehow highlighting friends and those you talk to most to make it easiest to contact them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is when I decided to dedicate the app to &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; those favorites that you contact the most.
Instead of having the whole muddled mess of contacts, probably over half of them you used exactly one
time and will never use again, Friends puts the people most important to you at your fingertips instantly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-features&#34;&gt;The Features&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the beginning I wanted to keep the app small and simple. I didn&amp;rsquo;t want anything slow and clunky with
a million unnecessary features that just ruin the user experience. I wanted the list of contacts as the
main screen, and when you click on one it will bring up their details and allow you to contact them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main feature is that it collects all your favorite contacts and puts them in a very simple list on
the main screen. It isn&amp;rsquo;t cluttered or messy, and it is very easy to glance through to find the person
you are looking for in a couple seconds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you find the person you are looking for you can click on them to open up the details screen. This
screen has their name, of course, in a very simple material designed way. It will also have a card
containing the last text message you received from them as a reminder to what you were last talking about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last thing you can do on the details screen is either call or text your friend. There is a Floating
Action Button on the screen, and when you click on it, it will expand showing a couple of options. You
can click the option on the left to call this person, or the option on the left to open your default
messaging app and text them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently that is all you can do, but there are plans to add new features in the future, as long as it
doesn&amp;rsquo;t complicate the feel. Something I&amp;rsquo;m already planning to implement is a long press to call from
the main contact list screen. Things like that are neat and useful tricks that don&amp;rsquo;t have any effect on
UI or performance but still positively improve the utility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;release-schedule&#34;&gt;Release Schedule&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned previously, I plan to have the first version of this released within the first week or
two of January. As with all software, it is never finished, but it is very nearly ready to be released
in the initial version. All of the features for the first version are already implemented and seem to
be working, but I might need to make a few tweaks here or there and I&amp;rsquo;m still heavily testing to make
sure it goes well on release.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll update this post frequently with news on the release schedule and probably continue to update it
after it is released to announce improvements and future features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Update&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Friends has officially been published to the Play Store. Of course it is a bare bones version, but there
will be more updates down the line. I did end up adding the long press to call from the main screen since
that was a very quick edit to the code. I also added a sorting function to put your friends in
alphabetical order. That was relatively simple to implement and makes it much easier to scroll and find
the person you are looking for. If you want to check it out please download it from the Play Store and
leave me a review letting me know what you think!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.software.rmh.friends&#39;&gt;&lt;img src=&#39;https://ryanmhoffman.github.io/img/google-play-badge.png&#39;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>