<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ryan M. Hoffman</title>
    <link>https://ryanmhoffman.github.io/tags/development/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Ryan M. Hoffman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright (c) 2016 RMH Companies; all rights reserved.</copyright>
    <atom:link href="https://ryanmhoffman.github.io/tags/development/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Friends Android App</title>
      <link>https://ryanmhoffman.github.io/blog/2016/12/20/friends-android-app/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Dec 2016 13:47:08 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ryanmhoffman.github.io/blog/2016/12/20/friends-android-app/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;friends-android-app&#34;&gt;Friends Android App&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Friends is an Android app I am currently developing with a planned release in early January 2017. The app
is a short-list version of the stock contacts app. Friends pulls in only your starred contacts and gives
you easy access to call or text them. It is supposed to be sort of like a speed dial, but for all your
favorites instead of just one, and all in one place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-idea&#34;&gt;The Idea&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I originally began building this app as a generic replacement to the stock contacts app on Android. As I
was building it I began wondering what feature I would have that would set it apart. I thought about the
idea of somehow highlighting friends and those you talk to most to make it easiest to contact them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is when I decided to dedicate the app to &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; those favorites that you contact the most.
Instead of having the whole muddled mess of contacts, probably over half of them you used exactly one
time and will never use again, Friends puts the people most important to you at your fingertips instantly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-features&#34;&gt;The Features&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the beginning I wanted to keep the app small and simple. I didn&amp;rsquo;t want anything slow and clunky with
a million unnecessary features that just ruin the user experience. I wanted the list of contacts as the
main screen, and when you click on one it will bring up their details and allow you to contact them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main feature is that it collects all your favorite contacts and puts them in a very simple list on
the main screen. It isn&amp;rsquo;t cluttered or messy, and it is very easy to glance through to find the person
you are looking for in a couple seconds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you find the person you are looking for you can click on them to open up the details screen. This
screen has their name, of course, in a very simple material designed way. It will also have a card
containing the last text message you received from them as a reminder to what you were last talking about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last thing you can do on the details screen is either call or text your friend. There is a Floating
Action Button on the screen, and when you click on it, it will expand showing a couple of options. You
can click the option on the left to call this person, or the option on the left to open your default
messaging app and text them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently that is all you can do, but there are plans to add new features in the future, as long as it
doesn&amp;rsquo;t complicate the feel. Something I&amp;rsquo;m already planning to implement is a long press to call from
the main contact list screen. Things like that are neat and useful tricks that don&amp;rsquo;t have any effect on
UI or performance but still positively improve the utility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;release-schedule&#34;&gt;Release Schedule&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned previously, I plan to have the first version of this released within the first week or
two of January. As with all software, it is never finished, but it is very nearly ready to be released
in the initial version. All of the features for the first version are already implemented and seem to
be working, but I might need to make a few tweaks here or there and I&amp;rsquo;m still heavily testing to make
sure it goes well on release.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll update this post frequently with news on the release schedule and probably continue to update it
after it is released to announce improvements and future features.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>